Guide to the Papers of Edward N. Gadsby 1956-1973 MC 175
New York University Archives
Edward N. Gadsby Papers
1956-1973
MC 175
New York University Archives
2.5 linear feet 2.5 linear feet ( 5 boxes)
This collection contains
Gadsby, Edward N., 1900-1973
Arrangement
Folders within each series are arranged chronologically.
The files are grouped into 3 series:
Correspondence
Newspaper Clippings
Publications
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains correspondence, published opinions, clippings, and speeches of Edward N. Gadsby. The collection has been divided into three series: Correspondence, Newspaper Clippings, and Publications. Correspondence includes letters during Gadsby's tenure on the Securities and Exchange Commission (SEC) as well as personal correspondence. Newspaper clippings include articles and excerpts from the North Adams Transcript during the early 1940s, when Gadsby was particularly active in local and state politics. The Publications Series contains several volumes of opinions authored by Gadsby when he was associated with the Massachusetts Department of Public Utilities, a bound set of his collected speeches as Chair of the SEC, and two editions of the Matthew Bender Business Organizations series, relating to the Security Exchange Act of 1934, which Gadsby edited and which include his handwritten edits.
Historical/Biographical Note
Edward Northup Gadsby was born in North Adams, Massachusetts. He graduated from Amherst College in 1923 and received his law degree from New York University in 1929. After practicing in New York for eight years, he returned to North Adams, where he practiced for 10 years (1947-1952) before being named to the Massachusetts Public Utilities Commission. From 1952-1956 he served as counsel to the commission.
In 1957 Gadsby was named by President Dwight D. Eisenhower to the Securities and Exchange Commission (SEC), and a year later became its chair. He resigned in 1961, shortly after he had relinquished the chairmanship upon the inauguration of President John F. Kennedy. He joined a private law firm, Colson and Morin, which had branch offices in Boston, Washington, and Puerto Rico and opened a small office in Williamstown, MA. In 1965, Gadsby closed the Williamstown office and moved to Cambridge, MA, where he continued as a partner in the firm. In 1972, Colson and Morin left to join Dickstein, Shapiro and Morin, Gadsby continued the firm under the name of Gadsby and Hannah.
In 1934, Gadsby married Isabella E. Halsey, and the couple had two children. Gadsby died in Boston, MA on June 12, 1973.
Sources:
Gadsby, Edward, Biographical File, NYU Archives.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions. This collection is in
off-site storage
.
Provenance
Edward N. Gadsby, Jr. donated this collection to the University Archives in 2004.
Gadsby, Edward N., 1900-1973; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Massachusetts. Dept. of Public Utilities; Publications.; speeches.; United States. Securities and Exchange Commission.
- Series I: Correspondence
  - Congratulatory Letters re: Appointment, Aug 1957-Oct 1957 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General note
    Barcode #: 3 1142 042266125
  - Reading File, Aug 1957-Dec 1957 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 042266112 5
  - Reading File, Jan 1958-Jun 1958 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Reading File, Jun 1958-Dec 1958 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Reading File, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Reading File, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - White House Correspondence, 1957-1961 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence re: NED's Death, 1968-1973 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 042266113 3
- Series II: Newspaper Clippings
  - NED - No. Adams Politics - 1940s (1 of 2), undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - NED - No. Adams Politics - 1940s (2 of 2), undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Amusing Incidents, 1956-1960 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Boston College Article "The Securities Exchange Commission", May 1970 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - New York Law School Article, 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Series III: Publications
  - Speeches of Edward N. Gadsby, Sep 1957-Dec 1960 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 042266114 1
  - Business Organizations: Federal Securities Exchange Act 1934, by Edward N. Gadsby, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Business Organizations: Federal Securities Exchange Act 1934, Cumulative Supplement, by Edward N. Gadsby, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Gadsby Opinions, Vol. I, pp. 1-167, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 042266115 8
  - Gadsby Opinions, Vol. II, pp. 168-412, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Gadsby Opinions, Vol. III, pp. 413-613, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Gadsby Opinions, Vol. IV, pp. 614-764b, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Gadsby Opinions, Vol. V, pp. 765-903, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 042266116 6
  - Gadsby Opinions, Vol. VI, pp. 904-1049, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Gadsby Opinions, Vol. VII, pp. 1050-1272, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Gadsby Opinions, Vol. VIII, pp. 1273-1504, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)